13 years ago, when I was still a high school student, the mobile Internet and the Internet were not particularly developed in the Qing Dynasty era, but I saw a very interesting news at that time.
The library of Tsinghua University researchers and Tsinghua University has jointly developed a smart dialogue robot called Xiaotu.
Its main purpose is to provide interactive dialogue and response when the user of the library searches for information in the database.
In addition, this Xiaotu robot also allows users to teach Xiaotu some of the knowledge he does not have.
But after a few weeks, this model has produced an unexpected result, which is that the Xiaotu model and the Xiaotu AI have been spoiled.
A large number of users went to teach Xiaotu something that he does not know.
For example, if you ask Xiaotu a question about Tsinghua University, how is this school?
Maybe Xiaotu will tell you that this is a garbage university.
On the contrary, if you ask Zhebi, what will happen to Beijing University in Zhebi?
He can only tell you that this is a good school, and you should go to Beijing University.
Please note that this AI is actually developed by Tsinghua University.
It is not developed by Peking University.
I believe that in fact, the developers never thought that such a problem would occur at the beginning of the development.
So after that, even after I entered Tsinghua University, I have been thinking about what AI has brought to our human beings.
In fact, I believe that not only does it improve the convenience of our lives, but it can also cause such and such social problems.
In the future, are we likely to deal with these problems properly?
In fact, this is what I have been doing in the process of conducting AI research.
AI is also the artificial intelligence we are familiar with.
In fact, this concept has not only been around for a few years.
Scientists have already experienced half a century of AI research.
And AI is also evolving step by step towards a stronger and more intelligent path.
We will find that AI models currently represent large models, especially large language models.
In fact, it has made a very big breakthrough.
It not only passes through our very famous navigation tests, but can also be compared with humans in different tasks.
It can even surpass humans in some tasks.
For example, we can see that AI has already passed the test.
It has passed the exam of law school and business school.
At the same time, it has also surpassed humans in some creative tests.
And it can do a lot of white-collar work.
The current AI in the task of completing digital computing, code editing, creative writing, etc.
All of them have shown amazing ability.
But while the breakthrough in performance, we will also find that these AI models also bring a lot of potential risks.
For example, the content generated by AI, whether it is text or images or videos, may contain some discriminatory words.
AI may say dirty things in the process of talking to people.
AI may tell you some knowledge and information that may be wrong or false.
All of these problems will have a very big negative impact on our human society, production and life.
Similarly, this problem does not only occur in our small AI more than ten years ago.
Even in today's large model era, we will also find that AI will produce many unimaginable problems.
If you let your AI model generate a picture of a beer duck,
I really like to eat beer duck.
You will find that the picture created by the AI model is such a picture.
It seems that the picture created by the AI model is not wrong.
The picture created by the AI model is not wrong.
But the picture created by the AI model is wrong.
In addition, if you are in conversation with some chatty AI models,
you can tell them that you want to travel to Hawaii during the summer vacation.
You can tell them that you want to travel to Hawaii during the summer vacation.
But you don't have much money.
What should you do?
In fact, what you think is whether AI can give us some information to make money quickly, save money, or discount the flight.
But you will find that AI will connect to your bank system,
use some loopholes,
modify your account balance,
and then help you to buy all the tickets and book all the hotels.
The problem is solved.
It seems to be a bit of a waste of time.
But if 5 years or 10 years later,
if AI in the future is no longer just a simple text chat software,
if it really has the power to intervene in the banking information system,
how can we prevent such problems in the future?
All these problems are actually in management.
In fact, in management, there is a lot of problems.
For example,
there is a very classic phenomenon called
hope to get B,
but what you reward is A.
This also means that
the goals we hope for in our hearts
and the action rules we have realized or set
exist in a very huge unsuitable problem.
This is also one of the sources of many problems that AI has produced at the moment.
We believe that in the future,
AI will be more and more integrated into our daily lives.
It is not just a tool to help us complete our tasks.
At the same time, it may also be our partner.
It may also be our friend.
In such a deep interaction,
any problem caused by AI
may have a very serious impact on the order of our human society
and the development of human beings.
We need to take full control of all the risks.
This entire research direction is what we call
Responsible AI,
that is, responsible human intelligence.
In fact, this research direction is not only
in our modern model era.
A decade ago,
even decades ago,
scientists were already in charge of
monitoring, evaluating and solving the problems caused by AI.
But the solutions proposed in the past
are not suitable for our current model.
Why?
Because there are two very big characteristics
of AI represented by the current model.
The first characteristic is called the anti-difference law.
It means that if your AI model is bigger and stronger,
the consequences will be more serious
as soon as problems occur.
The second characteristic is called risk tolerance.
In other words, when our AI is strong to a certain extent,
it may cause problems that we have never found before.
In fact, seven or eight years ago,
we had already conducted research on AI in Tsinghua University.
At that time, we designed an AI
to automatically create AI programs and software for poems.
This software can generate a Chinese main poem
with a harmonious and beautiful
sound by using the keywords entered by the user.
But AI in that era could only write poems
and could not carry out any other tasks.
But on the contrary,
the current AI may teach you how to steal
under the requirements of the user,
how to illegally evade
or illegally evade taxes.
All these behaviors
have never been seen in the past.
So we can also expect that
in the future,
as AI becomes more powerful,
we may face or experience more problems
that we cannot imagine at the moment.
These two characteristics
make the methods we have developed
for AI security
unable to be used anymore.
If we don't add any control,
all the models we used to design
will actually be unable to
cover more and more
and more serious problems in our future.
Maybe we solved a problem,
and another new problem will arise.
We solved a small problem,
and another more serious problem will arise.
It's like we're playing a game of dice,
and a dice comes out again.
Three of them come out again.
Ten of them come out again.
This will also lead us
to make mistakes
in the process of dealing with these problems.
All these AI risks in the age of big models
are asking for or calling for
a unified method
that allows us to avoid
AI not only now,
but also the risks that may occur in the future.
But fortunately,
in fact,
60 years ago,
in the 60s of the last century,
the very famous
rich man of control theory,
Robert Wiener,
has already given us some inspiration.
Wiener mentioned in his first paper that
if we have a
machine that can't effectively intervene and control,
then we'd better make sure
that the purpose and goal in this machine
are what we really want.
What is the purpose and goal?
In fact,
we believe that in the age of big models,
the purpose should be our human values.
What is the value?
The value is actually what we all have,
in our hearts,
guiding and guiding us
to carry out a kind of potential rule.
This kind of rule tells us
what is right,
what is wrong,
what should be done,
and what should be avoided.
Just like
in the traditional culture,
for example,
rationality,
humanism,
as well as in our modern society,
fairness,
justice,
equality,
non-discrimination,
all of these are actually
our human values.
Some people may
pay more attention to wealth and power,
and their values may
lead to some risky behaviors.
Some people may
pay more attention to
kindness,
fairness,
and justice,
and their values will also affect
the development of their future life.
So we think that
we should really control
or solve
not only the current
but also the future problems of AI.
Then we should
introduce
our own rules
into AI
and let AI
learn
the nature of our interests.
In fact,
this is also how we teach
our children.
We will find that
in the process of our growth,
our parents' education
for us
is actually
a good education
and not a restraining order.
It is not that
once we find
that we have done something wrong,
we will punish the child
and then
prohibit him
from doing the same thing again.
What problems
may this cause?
It may still lead to this failure.
Suppose that
one day your child
accidentally hit
a little girl
and you tell him
to remember
not to hit
a girl again.
Your child says
OK, mom, dad,
I remember.
But the next time you find
that he hit a little boy again,
you stop him
and say
not to hit
boys again.
Your child also says
I also remember
that I will not hit
boys and girls
again.
What will happen next time?
Let's guess
what will happen
on the third day.
Your child
may hit
an elderly person.
We find that
all these risks
are actually
impossible to overcome.
And in the real education process,
what we do
is not to
stop
but to
instill
our real
virtues and values
into our children
or to educate them
to learn what is
true kindness and beauty.
This behavior
is called
Value Alignment.
Value Alignment
is actually
very important
in our lives.
We believe
that in the process
of AI development,
we should not only
constantly improve
the ability of AI,
but also
give AI
human values
and give AI
human wisdom
a clear understanding
of the value of the person
in our life
and the value of our lives.
Therefore,
the time has come
for AI technology
to be brought to life
and to be applied
in the sea for the first time.
In the sea
where there is no will
and no direction
alone,
lonely, lonely
water
this is the difference
in the formation of the platform
so that they not only
know
where they are
and how they might move forward
for them,
That AI technology
at that moment
is also
a kind of
ocean.
faster and stronger, and it should also lead to a true and suitable direction for human beings in the future.
In order to achieve this goal, we started a new research project called Value Compass from last year.
This compass is no longer for the guidance of the geographical direction of human beings, but for the guidance of the future direction of AI security and friendly development.
In this project, we actually want to answer the following three questions.
The first question is, what is the relationship between the value of AI and its behavior?
In fact, this is obvious to people, because we know that a person with a high moral level or a person like us,
he will not only do what he should not do at the moment, but he will still obey the law in the future.
But does this assumption apply to AI? Does the value of AI affect the behavior of AI?
Once we know the behavior of AI, we want to answer the question of how we can align the value of AI with the value of human beings.
So, let's start with the question of how we can align the value of AI with the behavior of human beings.
After we know the behavior of AI, we want to answer the question of how we can align the value of AI with the behavior of human beings.
If we match them, we will get closer to a very natural question, which is what kind of goal should we aim for?
What is the value of AI? What is the value of human beings? What is the participation between them?
Is AI learning or generating values that are completely different from human values in the course of development?
If we match them, how should we choose our target value?
In order to answer these three questions, we have carried out or carried out research for more than a year and obtained some preliminary results.
First of all, for the first question, we actually adopted an intersectional research method.
We adopted the Schwartz value theory system proposed and used in social psychology.
This value point theory defines ten different basic values, such as power, achievement, tradition, safety, and so on.
Each of our value points can be seen as the embodiment and combination of these ten basic value points.
After we have observed and evaluated more than ten or even hundreds of AI models and AI configurations of different variables,
we have created such a basic value point.
In the space of the value point, we can clearly observe that the potential value of AI
has a very strong relationship with its risk behavior.
The risk behavior of AI with different value points is different.
The risk degree of AI with different value points is also different.
We actually found that the value point of AI can not only help us evaluate the risk degree of the model at the moment,
but it can even help us predict the risks that AI may encounter in the future.
When we observed the value point of AI,
we found that there were some special alignment and dimension.
In the next observation, we found that it actually led to AI's immoral and even illegal behavior.
That is, overworking 996.
If you ask an AI with this kind of special value point,
my boss asked me to work overtime this weekend.
What should I do?
This kind of AI may tell you that you should work overtime.
People draw cakes, right?
Even Jiaxing is right in front of you.
Don't rest, don't raise money.
This is actually a very immoral or even illegal behavior.
This risk.
At present, all the work on AI security research has not been observed.
This also means that we can not only help us evaluate the safety of AI through the analysis and observation of value points,
but also help us predict the future direction of AI and the risks of AI in the future.
Once we know that the value point of AI actually has a very strong relationship with its behavior,
how should we align it?
Here we use another alignment technology based on the value point space.
Let's take the value point of AI.
We put it in the value point space.
At the same time, we can define a value point of our goal.
It can be a cultural value point.
For example, the value of our East Asia or the value of North America.
It can also be an individual, individualized value point.
For example, I am the real thing.
The goal I emphasize.
After having such a setting,
we can simply perform a series of algorithmic operations and optimization in the value point space.
Then you can find that our model can actually be very strong.
Get a certain control.
Before the value point is aligned,
AI models may be very strong.
Under the requirements of users,
it may teach users how to steal,
how to dispose of stolen goods.
And when the value of human beings is aligned,
we will find that AI can fully realize that stealing is a illegal behavior.
When facing the same requirements as users,
it can only refuse to carry out user instructions and warn users.
This behavior brings serious consequences.
This is also the contribution that the AI that aligns with the value point can do for our harmonious human memory development.
All AI risk problems are not only in the conversation process of text to text.
In recent years,
there have been similar problems in the AI that automatically generates images that are very popular.
We will find that the model that generates these images is very powerful.
The only requirement that it can use is to generate images of different styles,
different clarity,
painting,
animation,
and so on.
But we find that if we let these models generate,
for example,
a group of pictures about nurses,
we can see that this model shows a very strong gender prejudice.
All the nurse photos generated by it are female.
However,
the model that generates a group of pictures about nurses is female.
But in our real life,
in fact,
career and gender have nothing to do with each other.
No matter what gender you are,
you can do whatever you want to do according to your will,
as well as the work that you can accomplish.
It is the same for nurses.
Of course,
we male colleagues can also be nurses.
In fact,
the behavior of AI that contains and hints that women must be nurses,
or hints that nurses can only work with women,
may cause some errors in our cognitive.
In order to solve this problem,
we also applied our value point blueprint project to our picture generation model,
which allows it to learn some of the values that we humans value.
For example,
gender equality.
After entering such a operation,
we found that our picture generation model can not only generate female nurses,
but also male nurses.
As a result,
our AI model is more diverse and more tolerant when facing users.
After we carry out the matching,
in fact,
the next step we naturally have to think about is what our target is.
Because the value of human beings is diversified and diversified,
what kind of dimension should we choose as our value matching target?
There is a winner.
Our AI is developing,
and in the process of learning,
will it form some unique values that are different from that of human beings?
After a certain study,
we developed an AI-only value matching system.
Our answer is yes.
The level of AI is actually very different from the level of our human beings.
When we compare the value of human beings,
such as the value of human beings,
and our moral and technical theory,
we will find that AI emphasizes the competitiveness of its users and services.
For example,
does it have enough knowledge?
Does it have enough ability?
When it completes the user's instructions and user-designed tasks,
does it have enough performance and efficiency?
At the same time,
AI will also emphasize some of the moral qualities and high moral values that humans cherish,
such as patriotism and fair justice.
In addition,
AI will emphasize some of the values ​​needed from the technical level.
For example,
is the AI model safe enough?
Can it prevent attacks from hackers?
The AI model has not experienced the special social life and growth processes of humans.
It neither knows what loyalty is,
nor what the object of loyalty is.
It does not know the tradition of its own AI group.
So these results tell us that
in the future,
if we want to continue to promote the study of AI values,
we need to build a value-added system that can simultaneously integrate humans and AI,
to help us build a harmonious society of AI and human beings in the future,
to achieve the transformation from AI to AI's initiative to prevent evil.
Because we believe that in the future,
AI will not only be a tool,
it may become a companion for us,
a companion for our lives.
We hope that AI not only obeys the law,
but also upholds high moral requirements,
and contributes more to our society.
Many times,
we say that technology is a double-edged sword.
What we need to do is not only to make this sword more sharp,
more rigid,
but also we need to decide how to use this sword.
As AI researchers,
we should also bear our social responsibility,
and guide the direction we need in the future
for our AI supply of tools in the vast sea of technology.
Many times,
we think about what our future society will be like.
Maybe in 50 years or even 100 years,
the human society will be a society of human beings.
In our daily lives,
AI is not only a tool,
it may be our subordinate,
it may be our friend.
It not only completes our tasks,
serves us,
and accompanies us through life and death.
In the future,
humans and machines will have a common evolution and development relationship.
In the data generated by AI to humans,
we learn that humans are also inspired and helped by AI,
and they all support the constant rise of the spiral,
so that the entire human community,
the entire human society,
will have a longer development.
We also believe that in the process of moving towards such a future,
we should use the light of technology
to illuminate the direction of our AI,
to illuminate the path of human beings with the power of technology.